Last week, we learned a number theory
that's needed for public key encryption.
上周我们学了公钥加密所需的数论知识
This week we're gonna put this knowledge
to work, and we're gonna construct a
这周我们要用这些知识了，我们将构建
number of secure public key encryption
schemes. But first, we need to define what
许多安全的公钥加密机制。首先，我们需要定义
is public key encryption, and what does it
mean for public key encryption to be
什么是公钥加密，以及安全的公钥加密是什么意思？
secure? So let me remind you that in a
public key encryption scheme, there is an
我提示大家，在公钥加密机制中
encryption algorithm which is usually
denoted by E, and there's a decryption
有一个加密算法记为E，还有个解密算法
algorithm which we denote by D. However
here, the encryption algorithm takes a
我们记为D。不过这里的加密算法
public key, while the decryption algorithm
takes a secret key. This pair is called a
取一个公钥为输入，而解密算法取一个私钥为输入
key pair. And the public key is used for
encrypting messages while the secret key
这一对叫做密钥对。公钥用于加密信息
is used for decrypting messages. So in
this case a message m is encrypting using
私钥用于解密信息。那么这里，一个明文m
the public key and what comes out of that
is the ciphertext c. And similarly the
使用公钥加密，得到密文c。类似地
ciphertext is fed into the decryption
algorithm and using the secret key, what
把密文c交给解密算法，使用私钥
comes out of the decryption algorithm is
the original message m. Now public key
解密算法的输出就是原明文m
encryption has many applications. Last
week we saw the classic application which
公钥加密有许多应用。上周我们看了经典的应用
is session setup, namely, key exchange and
for now we're just looking at key exchange
比如会话建立，密钥交换，目前我们只看了
that is secure against eavesdropping only.
And if you remember the way the protocol
仅对窃听攻击安全的密钥交换。如果大家还记得
works, basically Alice, what she would do
is she would generate a public key secret
这个协议的工作过程Alice会产生一个公钥、私钥对
pair. She would send the public key to
Bob. Bob will generate a random X, which
她会把公钥发给Bob.Bob会产生一个随机X
is gonna serve as their shared secret, and
then he sends X encrypted to Alice,
X被作为共享密钥，然后Bob把X加密后发送给Alice
encrypted under her public key. Alice can
decrypt, recover X and now both of them
使用Alice的公钥进行加密。Alice可以解密，还原X
have this shared secret X which they can
use to communicate securely with one
现在双方都有了这个共享密钥X了，他们可以使用它来安全的互相通信
another. The attacker, of course, all he
gets to see is just the public key, the
攻击者当然只能看到公钥
encryption of X under the public key, from
which he should not be able to get any
和使用公钥加密后的X，根据这些他不应该能
information about X. And we are going to
define that more precisely to understand
获得任何关于X的信息。我们要更精确地定义
what it means to not be able to learn
anything about X. Public key encryption
不能学到任何关于X的信息是什么意思
actually has many other applications. For
example, it's very useful in
公钥加密实际上有很多应用。例如
non-interactive applications. So think of
an email system for example. So here, Bob
它在非互动应用中非常有用。考虑一个电子邮件系统为例
wants to send mail to Alice, and as Bob
sends the email, the email passes from
这里Bob想发送电子邮件给Alice，随着Bob发送了这份邮件
mail relay to mail relay until finally it
reaches Alice, at which point Alice should
电子邮件经由一个个邮件中转点，最终到达Alice
decrypt. The way the email system is set
up, is designed for kind of
Alice可以解密之。这样建立的电子邮件系统
non-interactive settings where Bob sends
the email. And then Alice is supposed to
是为Bob发送邮件的非互动情形设计的
receive it. And Alice should not be to
communicate with Bob in order to decrypt
然后Alice应收到邮件，为解密邮件
the email. So in this case, because of the
non-interactivity, there's no opportunity
Alice不应与Bob通信。这里，因为这种非互动性
for setting up a shared secret between
Alice and Bob. So in this case, what would
没有建立Alice和Bob之间的共享密钥的机会
happen is, Bob basically would, would send
the email encrypted, using Alice's, public
这里Bob会发送加密的邮件，使用Alice的公钥
key. So he sends the email. Anyone in the
world can send the email encrypted to
他发送了邮件，世界上任何人可以发送加密后的电子邮件
Alice, encrypted using her public key.
When Alice receives this email, she uses
给Alice，使用她的公钥。当Alice接收到邮件时
her secret key to decrypt the ciphertext and recover the plain text message.
她使用她的私钥来解密密文，还原明文
Of course the one caveat in a system like
this is that in fact Bob needs to somehow
当然这种系统有一个警告，事实上Bob
obtain Alice's public key So for now we
are just going to assume Bob already has
需要通过某种方法知道Alice的公钥。目前我们还只是假设
Alice's public key, but later on,
actually, when we talk about digital
Bob已经有了Alice的公钥，但待会儿当我们讨论
signatures we're gonna see how, this can
actually be done very efficiently using what's
数字签名时，我们会看到，这点使用所谓的
called public key management and as I said
we'll actually get back to that at a later
公钥管理将非常有效，如我所说，我们待会再来看
time. But the main thing I want you to
remember, is that public key encryption is
我想让大家记住的主要是，公钥加密
used for session setup. This is very
common on the web, where public key
用于会话建立。这在网络上很普遍
encryption is used to set up a secure key
between a web browser and, and web server.
公钥加密用于建立起一个浏览器和网页服务器之间的安全密钥
And public key encryption is also very
useful for non-interactive applications,
公约加密对非互动的应用也很实用
where anyone in the world,
non-interactively, needs to send a message
这个世界的任何人，需要非互动的发送信息
to Alice, they can encrypt the message using
Alice's public key, and Alice can decrypt
给Alice时，可以使用Alice的公钥加密信息
and recover the plain text. So let me
remind you in a bit more detail what a
Alice可以解密并还原明文。那么我来提示大家
public key encryption system is. Well,
it's made up of three algorithms G, E, and
关于公钥加密系统的更多细节。公钥加密系统由三个算法构成G,E,D
D. G is called the key generation algorithm.
Basically what it will do is it will
G叫做密钥生成算法
generate this key pair, the public key and
the secret key. As written here, G takes
G会生成这个密钥对，即公钥和私钥。如此所写
no arguments, but in real life, G actually
does take an argument called the security
G无输入参数，但在现实中，G其实有一个参数
parameter which specifies the size of the
keys that are generated by this key
叫做安全参数，指定了这个密钥生成算法将要生成的密钥大小
generation algorithm. Then there are these
encryption algorithms as usual that take a
通常有这些加密算法
public key and a message and produce a
ciphertext in a decryption algorithm that
它们取一个公钥和明文为输入，产生一个密文
takes the corresponding secret key and a
ciphertext and it produces a corresponding
在解密算法中，取对应私钥和密文为输入
message. And as usual for consistency we
say that if we encrypt a message under a
产生对应明文。通常为求一致性，我们说如果我们使用一个给定的公钥加密了一个明文
given public key and then decrypt with a
corresponding secret key we should get the
然后我们用对应的私钥解密
original message back. Now what does it
mean for a public key encryption to be
我们可以获得原先的明文 现在 一个公钥加密是安全的 是什么意思呢
secure? I'm going to start off by
defining, security against eavesdropping.
我想先从定义对抗窃听的安全性出发
And then we're going to define security
against active attacks. So the way to
然后再定义对抗主动性攻击的安全性
define security against eavesdropping is
very similar to the symmetric case we've
定义对抗窃听的安全性 与对称密码的情况很类似
already this last week so we're gonna go
through this quickly just as a review.
上周我们已经看过 来快速回顾一下
Basically the attack game is defined as
follows. We defined these two experiments,
这个攻击游戏如下定义 我们定义两个实验
experiment zero and experiment one. At in
either experiment the challenger is gonna
实验0和实验1 在两个实验中
generate a public and a secret key pair. He's gonna give the public
挑战者都会生成一对公钥和私钥
key to the adversary. The adversary's
gonna output two messages m0 and m1 of
他把公钥给攻击者 攻击者产生两个信息m0和m1
equal length and then what he gets back is
either the encryption of m0 or the
长度相同 然后攻击者会得到m0或m1的加密
encryption of m1. In experiment zero he
gets the encryption of m0. In experiment
在实验0中 他会得到m0的加密
one he gets the encryption of m1. And then
the adversary is supposed to say which one
在实验1中 他会得到m1的加密 然后攻击者要识别
did he get. Did he get the encryption of
m0 or did he get the encryption of m1? So
他得到的是哪个信息的加密 他得到的是m0还是m1的加密
in this game, the attacker only gets one
ciphertext. This corresponds to an
那么在这个有效中 攻击者只会得到一个密文
eavesdropping attack where he simply
eavesdropped on that ciphertext C. And now
这个对应于窃听攻击中他监听的密文C
his goal is to tell whether the ciphertext
C i s the encryption of M0 or M1. No
现在他的目标是分辨出密文C是m0还是m1的加密
tampering on the ciphertext C is allowed
just yet. And as usual we say that the
对密文C的篡改是不被允许的 通常我们说
public key encryption scheme is
semantically secure if the attacker cannot
这个公钥加密机制是语义安全的 如果攻击者不能
distinguish experiment zero from
experiment one. In other words he cannot
区分实验0和实验1 换句话
tell whether he got the encryption of M0,
or the encryption of M1. Before we move on
他不能区分他获得的是m0还是m1的加密
to active attacks, I want to mention a
quick relation between the definition we
在我们讨论主动攻击之前 我想简单提一下这个定义
just saw, And the definition of, of
eavesdropping security for symmetric
与对称密码的窃听安全的定义之间的关系
ciphers. If you remember, when we talked
about eavesdropping security for symmetric
如果大家还记得 当我们讨论对称密码的窃听攻击时
ciphers, we distinguished between the case
where the key is used once, and the case
我们区分了两种情况 密钥只使用一次
where the key is used multiple times. And,
in fact we saw that, there's a clear
和密钥使用多次 事实上我们看到有明确的区分
separation. For example, the onetime pad.
Is secure if the key is used to encrypt a
例如 一次性密码本是安全的 如果密钥只被用于加密当个明文
single message, but is completely insecure
if the key is used to encrypt multiple
但如果密钥用于加密多个明文 将是不安全的了
messages. And in fact we had two different
definitions if you remember we had a
如果大家还记得 事实上我们有两个不同的定义
definition for one-time security, and then
we had a separate definition, which was
一个是一次性安全 还有另一个不同的定义
stronger, when the key was used multiple
times. The definition that I showed you on
更强一点 当密钥被使用多次
the previous slide's very similar to the
definition of one time security for
上一张幻灯片里的定义与对称密码的一次性安全很类似
symmetric ciphers. And in fact, it turns
out that for public key encryption, if a
事实上 对于公钥加密
system is secure under a onetime key, in a
sense, it's also secure for a many time
如果系统的一次性密钥是安全的 那么它对多次密钥也安全
key. So in other words, we don't have to
explicitly give the attacker the ability
换句话 如果我们不必赋予攻击者
to, request encryptions of messages of his
choice. Because he could just create those
请求加密他选择的明文的能力 因为他自己可以
encryptions all by himself. He is given
the public key, and therefore he can by
创建这些加密 他有了公钥 因此它可以
himself encrypt any message he likes. As a
result any public key secret pair in some
自己加密任何他喜欢的明文 因此从某种意义上
sense inherently is used to encrypt
multiple messages because the attacker
公钥私钥对天生就是用来加密多个信息的
could have just encrypted many, many
messages of his choice using the given
因为攻击者可以加密很多他选择的明文
public key that we just gave him in the
first step. And so, as a result in fact,
使用我们第一步给定的公钥 所以事实上
the definition of one time security is
enough to imply many time security and
一次性安全的定义足以蕴含着多次安全
that's why we refer to the concept as
indistinguishability under a chosen plain
这就是为什么我们称这个概念是选择明文攻击下的不可区分性
text attach. So this is just a minor point
to explain why the settings of public
这只是稍微解释下为什么在公钥加密的设定里
encryption, we don't need a more
complicated definition to capture
我们不需要更复杂的定义来理解窃听安全
eavesdropping security. Now that we
understand eavesdropping security, let's
现在我们理解了窃听安全性
look at more powerful adversaries that can
actually mount active attacks. So, in
我们来看一下更有力的可以产生实际攻击的对手
particular, let's look at the email
example. So here, we have our friend Bob
特别地，我们来看一下电子邮件的例子，那么这里我们有我们的朋友Bob
who wants to send mail to his friend
Caroline. And Caroline happens to have, an
他想给他的朋友Caroline发邮件。并且Caroline恰好有一个
account at Gmail. And the way this works
is basically, the email is sent to the
Gmail上的账户。过程如下，这个被加密的邮件
Gmail server, encrypted. The Gmail server
decrypts the email, looks at the, intended
被发送到Gmail的服务器上。服务器解密这封邮件，找寻预期的接收者
recipients. And then, if it's, the
intended recipient is Caroline, it
之后，如果是，预期接收者是Caroline，
forwards the email to Caroline. If the
intended recipient is the attacker, it
它就把邮件给Caroline。如果预期接收者是攻击者，
forwards the email to the attacker. This
is similar to how Gmail actually works
他就会把邮件交给攻击者。这很像Gmail的工作方式
because the sender would send the email
encrypted over SSL to the Gmail server.
因为发送者会发送通过SSL加密的邮件给Gmail服务器
The Gmail server would terminate the SSL
and then forward the email to the
Gmail服务器会中断SSL连接然后将邮件给
appropriate recipients. Now suppose Bob
encrypts the email using a system that
合适的接收者。现在假设Bob加密的邮件，使用的系统
allows the adversary to tamper with the
ciphertext without being detected. For
允许攻击者在不被探测到的情况下篡改密文。
example, imagine this email is encrypted
using Counter Mode, or something like
例如，假设这个邮件用计数模式加密的，或者类似的方法。
that. Then when the attacker intercepts
this email, he can change the recipient,
然后，当攻击者拦截这封邮件时，他可以改变接收者，
so that now the recipient says
attacker@gmail.com, and we know that for
因此现在接收者是attacker@gmail.com，并且我们知道对于
Counter Mode, for example, this is quite
easy to do. The attacker knows that the
计数模式，这样做是很容易的。攻击者知道
email is intended for Caroline, he is just
interested in the email body. So he can
邮件是发送给Caroline的，他只是对邮件内容感兴趣。因此，他可以
easily change the email recipient to
attacker@gmail.com and now when the server
简单的将邮件接收者改为attacker@gmail.com并且当服务器
receives the email, he will decrypt it,
see that the recipient is supposed to be
接收到邮件时，他将会解密邮件，看到接收者应该是攻击者
attacker, and forward the body to the
attacker. And now the attacker was able to
然后就将邮件给了攻击者。并且现在攻击者可以
read the body of the email that was
intended for Caroline. So this is a
阅读本来要送给Caroline的邮件的内容。所以这是一个
classic example of an active attack, and
you notice what the attacker could do
典型的主动攻击的实例，并且你可以注意到攻击者
here, is it could decrypt any ciphertext
where the intended recipient is to:
只能解密接收方是攻击者的密文
attacker. So any ciphertext where the plain
text begins with the words "to: attacker". So our goal is
也就是以“致攻击者”开头的明文所对应的密文。所以我们的目标是
to design public key systems that are
secure, even if the attacker can tamper
设计一个安全的公共密钥系统，即使攻击者可以篡改密文
with ciphertext and possibly decrypt
certain cyphertexts. And again, I want to
并且有可能解密某些密文。再次，我想要
emphasize that here the attacker's goal
was to get the message body. The attacker
强调攻击者的目的是得到明文的内容。攻击者
already knew that the email is intended
for Caroline. And all he had to do was
已经知道邮件的接收方是Caroline。并且他要做的只是
just change the, intended recipient. So
this tampering attack motivates the
改变接收方。因次这次篡改攻击就引入了
definition of chosen ciphertext security.
And in fact this is the standard notion of
选择密文安全的定义。事实上，这就是公钥加密安全性的
security for public key encryption. So let
me explain how the attack [here procedes] and as I
标准概念。那么让我解释这个攻击，
said our goal is to build systems that are
secure under this very, very conservative
如我所说我们的目标是建立一个在非常保守的加密概念下安全的
notion of encryption. So we have an
encryption scheme (G, E, D). And let's say
系统。因次我们有一个加密体系（G,E,D）。并且我们说
that's defined over a message space and
a ciphertext (M, C) and as usual we're
它在一个明文空间和一个密文（M,C）上定义的，并且像往常一样
gonna define two experiments, experiment
zero, and experiment one. So 'b' here
我们将定义两个实验，实验0，实验1.这里‘b’
says whether the challenger is
implementing experiment zero or experiment
表示挑战者是否执行了实验0或实验1.
one. The challenger begins by generating a
public key and a secret key, and then gives
挑战者最开始产生一个公钥和一个私钥，然后
the public key to the adversary. Now the
adversary can say, "Well, here are a bunch
将公钥给了攻击者。现在攻击者可以说：“这里有一系列
of ciphertexts, please decrypt them for
me." So here the adversary submits
密文，请为我解密”攻击者上传
ciphertext C1 and he gets the decryption
of ciphertext C1, namely M1. And he gets
密文C1并且得到了C1的解密，叫它M1。
to do this again and again, so he submits
ciphertext C2, and he gets the decryption,
然后他反复的操作，他上传密文C2，然后又得到解密的信息
which is M2, ciphertext C3, and he gets
the decryption M3, and so on and so forth.
M2，密文C3，然后得到M3，诸如此类。
Finally, the adversary says, "This
squaring phase is over," and now he
最后，攻击者说“游戏结束”，然后他
submits basically two equal length
messages, M0 and M1 as normal, and he
上传两个等长的明文M0和M1，
receives in response the challenge
ciphertext C, Which is the encryption of M
并且接收挑战密文C，
zero or the encryption of M one. Depending
on whether we're in experiment zero or
也就是m0或m1的加密。取决于我们在实验0还是实验1
experiment one. Now, the adversary can
continue to issue these ciphertext
现在攻击者可以继续提交密文询问
queries. So he can continue to issue,
decryption requests. So he submits a
因此他可以继续请求解密密文。所以他提交一个
ciphertext, and he gets a decryption of
that ciphertext, but of course, now, there
密文，之后得到密文的解密，当然，
has to be a caveat. If the attacker could
submit arbitrary ciphertext of his choice,
现在应该有一个警告。如果攻击者可以提交他选择的任意密文
of course, he could break the challenge.
What he would do is he would submit the
当然他可以破解挑战。他将要做的是上传一个
challenge ciphertext C as a decryption
query. And then he would be told whether
挑战密文C作为解密询问。然后他被告知
in the challenge phase he was given the
encryption of M0 or the encryption of M1.
他在挑战阶段获得的是M0还是M1的加密结果
As a result we put this limitation here,
that says that he can in fact submit any
因为我们有这么一个限制，攻击者可以提交
ciphertext of his choice except. For the
challenge ciphertext. So the attacker
任何他选择的密文，除了挑战密文
could ask for the decryption of any
ciphertext of his choice other than the
那么攻击者可以询问他选择的任何密文的解密
challenge ciphertext. And even though he
was given all these decryptions, he still
除了挑战密文。即使攻击者有所有这些的解密
shouldn't be able to tell whether he was
given the encryption of M0 or the
他依然不能分辨出他得到的是M0还是M1的加密
encryption of M1. So you notice this is a
very conservative definition. It gives the
所以大家注意，这是一个非常保守的定义
attacker more power than what we saw in
the previous slide. On the previous slide,
它赋予了攻击者比我们上一张幻灯片里看到的更多的能力
the attacker could only decrypt messages
where the plain text began with the words
上一张幻灯片里，攻击只能解密以“致攻击者”开头的信息
"to: attacker". Here, we're saying the attacker
can decrypt any ciphertext of his choice,
这里，攻击者可以解密任何他选择的密文
as long as it's different from the
challenge ciphertext C. Okay? And then his
只要提交的密文与挑战密文C不同
goal is to say whether the challenge
ciphertext is the encryption of M0 or the
然后攻击者的目标是，判断挑战密文是M0还是M1的加密
encryption of M1. And as usual, if he
can't do that, in other words, his
通常，如果攻击者不能做到，换句话说
behavior in experiment zero is basically
the same as his behavior in experiment
他的表现在实验0和实验1中是一样的
one, so he wasn't able to distinguish the
encryption of M0 from the encryption of
那么他不能区分M0与M1的加密
M1, even though he had all this power Then
we say that the system is chosen
即使他拥有这么多的能力。那么我们说
ciphertext secure, CCA secure. And
sometimes there is an acronym, the acronym
这个系统是选择密文CCA安全的。有时有一个缩写词
for this is indistinguishability under a
chosen ciphertext attack, but I'm just
对选择密文攻击的不可区分性
gonna say CCA secured. So let's see how
this captures, the email example we saw
我记为CCA安全。那么我们看这如何抓住了我们前边看的电子邮件的例子的特点
before. So suppose the encryption system
being used is such that just given the
那么假设使用的加密系统满足
encryption of a message the attacker can
change the intended recipient from to
给定信息的加密，攻击者可以改变接收方
Alice say to, to Charlie. Then here's how
we would win the CCA game. Well in the
从“致Alice”改为“致Charlie”,那么我们可以这样赢得游戏
first step he's given the public key of
course. And then what the attacker will do
第一步攻击者当然得到了公钥，
is he would issue two equal length
messages, namely in the first message, the
然后攻击者会发出两个等长度的密文，第一个明文内容是0
body is zero. In the second message the
body is one. But both messages are
第二个明文内容是1   两个明文都给Alice
intended for Alice. And in response, he
would be given the challenge ciphertext C.
Alice回复后，攻击者会得到密文C
Okay, so now here we have our challenge
ciphertext C. Now what the attacker is
那么现在我们有挑战密文C了
gonna do is he's gonna use his, his
ability here to modify the intended
现在攻击者会使用他的能力去修改接收方
recipient. And he's gonna send back a
ciphertext C', where C' is the encryption
他会返回给Alice一个密文C'
of the message to Charlie with body being
the challenge body b. So if you remember is
C'是Charlie的明文加密结果，其内容是挑战密文的内容b
either zero or one. Now, because the plain
text is different, we know that the
如果大家记得是0还是1  现在因为明文不同
ciphertext must also be different. So in
particular, C prime must be different from
我们知道密文也不同  那么特别地
the challenge ciphertext C, yeah? So the
C prime here must be different from C. And
C'一定和挑战密文C不一样，对吧？那么C'一定不同于C
as a result, the poor challenger now has
to decrypt by definition of the CCA game.
因此可怜的挑战者现在必须解密，根据CCA游戏的定义
The challenger must decrypt any ciphertext
that's not equal to a challenge
挑战者必须解密任何不同于挑战密文的密文
ciphertext. So the challenger decrypts
give the adversary M prime. Basically he
那么挑战者解密了，给攻击者解密结果M'
gave the adversary B, and now the
adversary can output the challenge B and
他给了攻击者B，现在攻击者可以输出挑战结果b
he wins the game with advantage one. So
he's advantage with this particular scheme
他以优势1赢得了这个游戏，那么他对这个游戏的优势是1
is one. So, simply because the attacker
was able to change the challenge ciphertext
因为攻击者能够改变挑战密文
from one recipient to another that
allows him to, to win the CCA game with
从一个接收方改到另一个，使得他能以优势1赢得这个CCA游戏
advantage one. So as I said, chosen
ciphertext security turns out actually is
如我所说，选择密文安全事实上是
the correct notion of security for public
key encryption systems. And it's a very,
公钥加密的正确的观念
very interesting concept, right? Basically, somehow
even though the attacker has this ability
这是个非常有趣的概念，对吧？即使攻击者有这能力
to decrypt anything he wants. Other than
the challenge ciphertext, still he can't
能解密任何他想解密的密文，挑战密文除外
learn what the challenge ciphertext is.
And so the goal for the remainder of this module
他依然不能学到挑战密文是什么。那么本章余下的目标
and actually the next module as well, is
to construct CCA secure systems. It's
其实也包括下一章，目标是构建CCA安全的系统
actually quite remarkable that this is
achievable and I'm going to show you
很惊人的是，这是可以做到的
exactly how to do it. And in fact those
CCA secure systems that we build are the
我会告诉大家怎么做。事实上我们构建的这些CCA安全系统
ones that are used in the real world. And
every time a system has tried to deploy
就是在现实中使用的系统。每次系统试图
a public key encryption mechanism that's not
CCA secure someone has come up with an
布置一个不是CCA安全的公钥加密机制时
attack and was able to break it. And we're
going to see some of these example attacks
都有人提出攻击并破解了它
actually in the next few segments.
下面几节我们将看到这些攻击的几个例子